- Previously on Gotham...
- I saw a vision
of a cataclysmic event.
(gunshot)
BRUCE: We will create
a legacy in this city.
I think you could be so strong.
He sees it, too.
BULLOCK: Jeremiah
escaped. He's got Bruce.
JEROME: I have bombs
planted around the city.
I know seeing is believing,
and I do want you to believe me,
so...
HARLAN: Now, the governor's
declared the city off-limits
until the situation
can be evaluated.
- In two hours, this city's
gonna be a battleground.
- Well, I'm not leaving.
RA'S AL GHUL: Gotham is
soon to be each man for himself,
a more savage place.
(grunts)
What should I do with you?
OSWALD: You took
away the one person I love,
so I took the one
person you love.
Out of this crucible of blood
will rise the dark knight
that your city needs.
Gotham falls. We rise.
(horns honking)
(sirens wailing)
♪♪
- ♪ We'll meet again ♪
- (gunshots)
♪ Don't know where ♪
♪ Don't know when ♪
♪ But I know we'll meet again ♪
♪ Some sunny day. ♪
(record skips, music stops)
(sirens wailing)
♪♪
Fire on my command!
(guns clicking)
For Gotham.
♪♪
MAN (over radio):
Listen, Gordon.
Your people decided to
ignore evacuation orders...
GORDON: No, no, no, no, no.
It is clear you
don't understand.
MAN: What's to
understand, Mr. Gordon?
I'm afraid you are
not making your...
GORDON: For the last time,
after the bridges blew
and the government
declared Gotham off-limits,
the city was up for grabs.
Given over to
criminals and murderers.
Now, territory is
controlled by whoever has
enough power to hold it.
(scoffs) I mean, we have Penguin
in City Hall, for God's sakes.
He raided the armory
and stockpiled weapons,
then repurposed a factory
to manufacture ammunition.
(gunshot)
It's made him unassailable.
Barbara and the Sirens
control an area around their club.
It's the only place in
Gotham not suffering for food,
or booze.
Barbara trades
mainly in information.
Just be gone by midnight.
It's women only, but men
can buy windows of time.
It's two minutes past
pumpkin time, sweetheart.
- Wait.
- GORDON: Word is...
(grunting)
she enforces her
rule with an iron hand.
To the west is Jonathan Crane,
the Scarecrow.
(grunting and groaning)
(growls)
(man whimpering,
pleading indistinctly)
(all cheering)
(screaming)
Victor Fries is further north
and warring with Firefly.
And to date, there have
been no confirmed sightings
of Jeremiah Valeska.
Then there's us.
GCPD controls a ten-block
area around the precinct,
where we feed and
protect 150 civilians.
That number could grow as
who knows how many others
are trapped around the city.
These are people
who couldn't get out
when the city was abandoned.
The poor, the
sick, whole families.
The government has a duty.
You have a duty to help them.
MAN: Mr. Gordon...
Captain Gordon.
MAN: We've been over
this time and time again.
No one is allowed
in or out of Gotham.
People we are protecting
are not criminals.
MAN: And anyone who
stayed after the evacuation order
is no longer the
government's responsibility.
We are surrounded
by hostile forces.
We are running out
of food, ammunition.
There are children here.
You have to evacuate them.
MAN: A committee is being formed
regarding the
situation in Gotham.
(quietly): Committee.
At least let us
resupply ourselves.
MAN: We understand
the situation.
You don't understand.
If you did, you
would do something.
Just say we're on our own.
(radio static warbling
and crackling)
DOCTOR: Paralysis
aside, we need to operate
before her spine
collapses upon itself.
In truth, she should
have been evacuated.
ALFRED: Yeah, well,
we tried to get her out
the night that
everything went to hell.
And then they blew
the bloody bridges.
BRUCE: Can you operate here?
I don't think we have a choice.
Selina?
(shuddering breaths)
The doctor wants to operate.
Fine.
Whatever.
I'm gonna be here
the whole time.
(angry shouting)
Enough!
You cops are getting fat
while the rest of
us are starving!
That's right.
While the rest of
us are starving!
- You hungry? Yeah?
- (clamoring continues)
- The cops get more!
- I got something
you can chew on.
Harvey, Harvey! May I? May I?
Everyone. Sir?
- Everyone gets the same share,
police and civilians alike.
- (others jeering)
If we start handing out
more, the supplies will not last.
You're lying. He's lying!
The cops get more.
- You shut up!
- GORDON:
That's enough!
(clamoring quiets)
You don't like the rules, leave.
I'm just saying...
Say it walking, putz.
(scattered shouts)
MEN: Come on!
MAN: You look well fed!
Let's go.
OFFICER: Hey,
come on, listen up.
Move it out of here.
Move it.
(door closes)
GORDON: So, how we doing?
LUCIUS: Well, we
got a month of food left.
Less if refugees keep coming.
What'd the Department
of Douchebaggery say?
GORDON: Same as always.
Not sending any help.
Not letting anyone leave.
- I had to try.
- I swear to God,
I am never paying taxes again.
And if people ask?
Tell 'em sooner or later,
the government
will do the right thing.
Rebuild the bridges,
take back the city.
Just have to be patient.
And the truth? We're on our own.
The truth is we have no
idea what might happen.
And our job is to
keep ourselves...
and everyone else alive.
BULLOCK: We're down to our
last rounds of ammo. What if...
Penguin or someone else
decides to make a move?
We're sitting ducks here, man.
♪♪
(birds squawking,
buoy bell clanging)
(snores, moans)
(wings fluttering,
pigeons cooing)
(gasps, grunts)
(sofa creaking)
(siren whooping, engine revving)
♪♪
(gasps)
(sighs)
- (dog growling)
- (gasps)
(barking)
♪♪
NYGMA: Okay.
Where was I?
Happened again.
This time, woke up on a rooftop.
Same thing.
No idea how I got there
or what happened during
the preceding hours.
Show yourself.
I know it's you
inside there, Ed.
Show yourself.
Idiot Ed still won't appear.
Coward.
But I know it's him controlling
me when I'm sleeping.
Why?
What is he doing?
You know, you could get
someone else to turn on the spotlight.
I like doing it.
Because it reminds people
that even in darkness,
there is light.
And it reminds me.
We're low on supplies.
Government won't
evac, won't send in help.
It doesn't make sense.
I imagine, from where they sit,
it's pretty easy to
ignore people's suffering.
I gave Lucius permission to raid
the Wayne Enterprises R & D lab
for whatever he could scavenge.
He's working on night
vision goggles for your men.
- It's not much.
- Everything helps.
Bruce, we stayed because people
here still here need protection.
That hasn't changed.
I should go.
The doctor's worried Selina's
condition is getting worse.
They're going to operate.
Let me know how it goes.
Are you sorry you stayed?
No.
You?
Hell no.
MR. PENN: Mr. Cobblepot
offers a thousand rounds
of freshly minted
nine-millimeter stock
for a thousand pounds
of grade-A steak.
Hmm, so what
we're hearing is true.
Cupboard's a bit
bare in Penguinland?
Absolutely not.
Mr. Cobblepot just had
a hankering for red meat.
Ugh, please. Ozzie
wants to get fat on rib eye
while his minions
starve. Shocker.
TABITHA: I have a question.
Why hasn't your boss left his
citadel since the bridges blew?
He scared I'm gonna
stick him in the throat?
BARBARA: Tabby's still
raw from when Penguin
murdered Butch
right in front of her,
so it'll have to
be 2,000 rounds.
Barbara, we're not giving
that bastard anything.
Exactly. We're trading
for something we need.
No.
Honey, no one is asking you
to forget what happened,
but how do we protect the
women who come in here every day
looking for safety?
We need this.
Penguin's time will come.
I promise.
(scoffs)
He's gonna regret
giving me this.
Better make it 3,000 rounds.
(indistinct radio chatter)
OFFICER: Something's out there.
- There. See? The shadow moved.
- (second officer laughs)
It's just a shadow, man.
No. Something's out there.
There. See?
(growls)
(screaming)
Hey, you okay?
(screaming continues)
You okay?
Would you like
me to make it stop?
(whimpering): Yes.
Open this door.
(grunting)
No, no, no! Don't open the gate!
(alarm buzzing)
(groaning)
Split up. Take what we came for.
Kill whoever stands in your way.
Show these fools
the face of fear.
(others shouting)
These here are the weak points.
Reinforce all barriers that
front Penguin's territory.
I want to be ready.
(electrical buzzing
and whirring)
HARPER: What the hell?
(quiet, indistinct chatter)
Find Lucius.
Tell him to meet
me at the generator.
(machine beeping)
Lights are out everywhere.
Well, don't you
worry, Master Bruce.
Clinic's got its own
backup generator.
(clanking, electrical buzzing)
You see?
Everything's shipshape
and Bristol fashion.
No.
Something's wrong.
Men in the basement.
They're stealing
all the medicine.
Alfred, stay with Selina.
Of course, but you
can't go down there.
It's gonna be pitch black.
Gonna need a torch or something.
Lucius gave me something better.
- Careful.
- (door closes)
(door creaking)
(door closes)
(buzzing, crackling)
(metallic scraping
and clanging; grunting)
I know what you're
thinking, Captain.
I have so few bullets.
Do I spend one on him?
Is it worth it?
I already know it's not.
My other question is:
Why are you here? It's
not to steal the generator.
Why would I want light?
Fear lives in darkness.
So what then? You
came for our supplies?
Exactly so.
But since I'm here,
I'll also take your life.
(grunting)
It's been a while since you
tasted my toxin, Captain.
What are you scared of now?
Not you.
(screaming)
(explosive whoosh)
(frantic chatter)
Hey! Hey!
- (gunfire, bullets ricocheting)
- Hey!
They got the beans.
(quiet, indistinct chatter)
Go. The lights are back up.
Go! Move! Go!
(high-pitched whirring)
(gasps) Did...
did you hear that?
(yells)
(grunting)
Hello?
Scag?
Hey... hey, guys?
Hey, guys, this
isn't... this isn't funny.
(grunting)
- (high-pitched ringing)
- (screams)
(grunting, gasping)
Go back! Go back!
(panting, frantic chatter)
(tires squealing,
sirens wailing)
(clamoring)
First their government
abandons them,
and then some freak
dressed like a scarecrow
steals their grub.
I'd be pissed, too.
So where are we?
At current consumption,
we've got a week of food.
Go to half rations.
We're already at half rations.
Cut 'em again.
The people won't be happy.
I haven't been
happy in ten years.
At least they'll be alive.
All right, that buys us
two weeks. Then what?
Jim, at this point,
the bastards across the
river are gonna have to
- step up and help.
- Why start now?
They haven't before.
For the love of God,
we... because we stayed
to do the job they wouldn't.
Huh? And now they're just
gonna sit back and watch
while we starve or
tear ourselves apart?
Because that's
what's gonna happen.
I know, Harv.
But right now, we have to
tell these people something.
BRUCE: Tell them help is coming.
I'll fly in supplies.
We tried that.
We couldn't even get
permission to take off.
Zero tolerance.
Nothing in or out.
BRUCE: Well, I'm not
asking for permission.
It's ready.
Alfred's already radioed
to have it delivered
from our east bay hangar.
We can have a supply
chopper here within hours.
Man, it is nice to have
a billionaire around.
Even if it succeeds,
the government's gonna find out.
It's a one-time solution.
Scarecrow's men
didn't just take food.
They stole medicine
from the clinic.
There are people in pain.
Harvey, tell the people
help is on the way.
You got it.
How's Selina?
She's strong.
She'll pull through.
Doc says the surgery
was a success.
My spine's not
gonna turn to jelly.
Still never be able
to walk again, so...
that's a bummer.
There's limited resources here.
But there's hope once
we join the mainland.
Gee.
For a second
there, I was worried.
Selina, I know you're in pain.
Some medicine is on its way.
You know what's funny?
Jeremiah shot me to get to you.
After all the
things I've done...
what did me in was
being your friend.
I just wish Jeremiah killed me.
Doctors can't help her.
She needs the witch.
(indistinct chatter)
MAN: Thank you.
How's the mood?
They're hanging in there.
They love their Jim Gordon.
But if that chopper
doesn't come, it'll be bad.
It'll come.
(operatic music playing)
(groans)
Feels good.
Missing something, though.
Put a knife on it.
- (laughing)
- (door opens)
Another shutdown at the factory.
A worker fell into
a hydraulic press.
It appears he passed
out from hunger.
Sir, I worry if we don't
increase the food allowance...
Mr. Penn,
I feel for all of our workers.
But I cannot give
what I do not have.
Overcooked!
(dog pants, whines)
(sighs)
Edward.
(laughs)
Such a good boy.
(laughing)
Quality at the factory
is also suffering.
- More misfires...
- Nonsense.
- (gunshot)
- (whimpers)
Our rounds are fine.
And now you've upset Edward.
- (pops)
- (groans)
As you see,
more misfires.
- Sir, if we don't
give better quality...
- Shut up.
Sir?
- Sir?
- Shh, shut up!
Shut up.
Do you hear that?
(exhales)
You said yourself, Penguin
has locked himself in City Hall
- with a small army.
- I know that.
- And I know you miss Butch.
- Do you?
Because he only
did it to hurt me.
That's why I have
to make it right.
And how are you gonna
do that and not get killed?
I need you, too.
(helicopter whirring
faintly in distance)
(whirring grows closer)
Tabby, you hear me?
Is that a chopper?
There it is.
This is Bruce Wayne.
I'm at the GCPD. We can see you.
PILOT (over radio):
Copy that, Mr. Wayne.
We'll meet you at
the rendezvous point.
PILOT: Mayday! Mayday!
We've been hit!
We're going down hard.
- Harvey, the chopper went down.
- PILOT: Mayday! Mayday!
GORDON: Get a team together now.
PILOT: Brace for
impact. We're going down.
Oh, my God.
Chopper went down
in Lo Boyz territory.
I expect we'll have to
fight our way in and out.
I know it's a lot to ask,
but without those
supplies, we're done.
Can we get some more ammo?
We're running dry down here.
Be happy you got
what you got, and get in.
GORDON: Alfred, I
expected to see Bruce here,
- wanting to come along.
- Well, you'd think,
wouldn't you?
I mean, his chopper, his pilots.
Maybe he thought
you wouldn't allow it.
(engines starting)
Just keep an eye on
things while I'm gone.
(sirens whooping)
(whirring, crackling)
(indistinct chatter)
(tires squealing)
(car doors open)
Hello.
The Lo Boyz, is it?
(chuckles)
I suspect you know who I am.
This ain't your turf, bird man.
OSWALD: Be that as it may,
I'm here to claim that.
Like hell.
(sighs)
(men shouting, grunting)
Get it in the truck.
(tires squeal, siren whoops)
Oswald!
Jim.
I thought you might show up.
It is so good to
see you, old friend.
How are you faring in
these troubled times?
Tell your men to step
away from the chopper.
Sorry. Mouths to feed.
And you know all
about that, don't you?
I hear you are up
to your ears in refugees.
We're protecting
children, families.
We need those supplies.
You shouldn't have
shot it down, Oswald.
You think I did this? (laughs)
No, no, no, no, no.
That would mean that I
knew a chopper was coming,
which I did not. I mean,
don't get me wrong,
we're still taking everything,
but I did not fire the shot.
It was an RPG.
Who else has that
kind of firepower?
Fair point.
But if it was me,
wouldn't I just admit it?
(laughing): I mean,
it's not like I'm
going to be arrested.
Then who was it?
No idea.
Now, nice as it was catching up,
it's time you skedaddle.
While you can.
We are, uh, kind of
outgunned here, partner.
OSWALD: Listen to Harvey.
After all we have been through,
do not make me kill you.
Not like this.
(whooshing) (men groaning)
(grunting and groaning)
(gasping)
- You should've stayed home.
- Listen to me.
I know you're upset about Butch.
(grunts)
He thought you were his friend!
- I was his friend!
- Liar!
You put a knife in
my mother's back.
His blood is on your hands!
You really think that I expected
to come here and walk away?
Jim, are you just
going to let her
kill me like this in cold blood?
Jim, listen to me. You
are not the only one
keeping Gotham from the abyss.
I am! I provide stability!
(gasps, pants)
I may have pulled the trigger,
but you killed Butch.
Shut up and die.
(pops, crackles)
(laughing)
(grunting)
Now, if that was
one of my bullets,
I will certainly be having
a word with my foreman.
Unacceptable!
Say hello to Butch.
(strained grunting)
BARBARA: No...!
♪♪
(whispering): Barbara...
don't...
(screaming)
- (Barbara screaming)
- (gunshots)
- I'm out.
- Me, too.
OSWALD: Uh-oh, Jim!
Sounding a little
quiet over there!
What the hell do we do now?
(gunfire continues in distance)
(grunting and groaning)
(screaming)
(yells in pain)
I know, I shouldn't
be here. But look.
Penguin had a truck
out back. I took these.
And there's more.
I could kiss you, kid.
OSWALD: For the
record, this is not
how I wanted things to go.
You son of a bitch.
I will rip out your heart!
Quiet. Now, that is
exactly the kind of talk
that's gonna force my hand.
But for old time's sake,
I will give you a chance.
Can we move past this?
Say the whole
Tabitha-Butch chapter is over?
I am gonna feed your guts
to the rats,
you beaky-nosed freak!
So, no.
What's the plan, boss?
Cover me.
GORDON: Oswald!
I want to make a deal.
(chuckling): A deal, Jim?
We split whatever's
in the chopper 50-50...
and you let Barbara go.
No.
He does not get to
limp out of here alive!
(grunts)
Shh!
I got a deal for you, Jim.
She dies, I take everything,
and you go home and reflect
long and hard
on my generosity.
And if I say no?
What happens when
the government finds out
you murdered the only
cops left in Gotham?
(laughing): Nothing.
Jim, as far as I can tell,
you have nothing to offer,
and you're out of ammo.
(shrieking)
Not anymore.
Truth is, I was never
gonna make that deal.
I need all those
supplies. Load up!
(screams)
(dogs barking)
MAN: We got it.
Here we go, people.
- Heads up.
- WOMAN: Finally, here we are.
BULLOCK: You think
Penguin's gonna pull through?
Cockroaches are hard to kill.
But at least he'll be out
of commission for a while.
You had him dead to rights.
You could've put
him down for good.
Yeah, shot a man
without warning.
Three months ago, I
would've lost my badge for that.
Three months ago, we
weren't fighting for our survival.
You think it didn't
cross my mind?
I know what we're
up against, Harvey.
No one is coming to help.
Then why didn't
you do us all a favor
and put that murdering
son of a bitch in a hole?
You want rules for
this game? I'll tell you.
I'll make it simple,
okay? You win or you die.
Next time, shoot to kill.
♪♪
Everything all right?
No, but we're alive,
so that's something. What's up?
The-the medicine's just
been taken to the clinic.
- I need to check on Selina.
- Yeah, sure.
I'll get you a ride.
- Hey! Let me know how she is.
- All right.
And, Bruce?
Next time you want
to help, just ask.
You've earned a place here.
♪♪
WOMAN (over radio):
Captain Gordon?
Hello? Captain Gordon, come in.
(radio static warbling
and crackling)
Captain Gordon, do you read me?
Hello? Come in.
This is James Gordon.
Who am I speaking to?
A friend who wants you to know
you have allies
across the river.
We will find a way to help you.
And who are you?
(radio crackling)
♪♪
(birds cawing, dogs barking)
(muttering, humming)
(grunts)
(cat meowing nearby)
(gasps)
- Get out of here!
- (gasps, whimpers)
Really?
A dumpster?
(panting)
(sighs): Okay.
(shouts)
What are you doing to me?!
Show yourself!
What is happening to me?
♪♪
I promise...
if it's the last thing I do...
I will kill him!
(Oswald screaming)
Aah! My leg!
He shot my leg!
I just fixed this!
Mr. Cobblepot, if
you could hold still, I...
Put out the word.
100,000 rounds of ammunition
to whoever kills Jim Gordon.
I want his head.
(screaming)
(wheels squeaking)
(door creaks shut)
(gasps, grunts)
(grunts)
(Selina screaming, sobbing)
No!
- Selina.
- DOCTOR: Help!
Let me go!
- Selina. Selina.
- Let me go!
Selina...
(crying): You can't
do this. Please.
(crying continues)
I have no reason to...
I can't...
(gasping)
You should've just let me do it.
Let her do what?
What happened?
She was trying to kill herself.
I'll get restraints
for when she wakes.
♪♪
(door creaks open)
I told you, you
want to cure her,
you have to go to the witch.
And where do I find this witch?
(birds squawking)
- Thank you so much.
- No problem.
Thank you very much.
Saint Jim of Gotham. All right.
Hey. Every new refugee who
comes in, I want questioned.
I need information
on Jeremiah Valeska.
I haven't heard
that clown's name
in three months. Why now?
Just call it a hunch.
Well, rather than a week
of food, we've got six weeks.
It's not a lot.
Yeah, but it's
better than we were.
Don't give up hope.
MAN: Captain Gordon!
Captain Gordon!
What's going on?
MAN: I was on duty
at the Thompson
Street barricade.
(panting): He just appeared.
He said he needed to see you.
What happened, son?
Where'd you come from?
(whispers): Past
the train station.
BULLOCK: That's on
the other side of town.
This kid must've made it through
half a dozen
sectors to get here.
My brothers and sisters.
They're killing us.
Who is?
You have to help us.
Whoa, whoa.
Get him to the clinic.
(gasps, coughs)
I know you're all asking,
why are we still here
when our own
government won't help us?
It's simple.
We're supposed to be
giving these people hope.
Hope that if they're in
danger, someone will come.
We will come.
Suit up!